Coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
This is the science fiction radio show, a
commentary on science fiction and fantasy.
And here are your hosts.
This is Daryl Lane.
And Bill Vernon.
You'll sometimes find that collectors of
science fiction and fantasy books are into
comics also.
In fact, collecting comics is becoming a
more widespread hobby all the time, and
often you'll find collectible comics at a
specialty store that handles science
fiction, fantasy, and gaming material.
Bob Wayne owns such a store in Fort Worth,
Texas, called Fantastic Worlds Bookstore.
And he also collects comics. When
he asked him how an interested newcomer
might get into comic book collecting, he
had some words of caution.
Well, the first recommendation that I make
to people if they come in and say,
I read that uh so and so comic book has
gone up a thousand percent in two years.
You know, what comic book would you
recommend that I should start collecting?
I tell people that
they really shouldn't be buying comics
unless they enjoy reading comics.
And if there's nothing in that comic book
they enjoy reading,
then
they're making a mistake getting into
comics because there are other things they
could invest money in
that uh that people will not laugh at you
when you go to the bank and tell them that
you want to use it for collateral.
So comic books as an investment is the
kind of thing that's really been
overplayed in the media to some extent.
I mean, it sounds real good for the few
comics that have appreciated a great deal
of value, but uh speaking from experience,
a bank does not really think that that's
the kind of collateral they want to hold
for a loan.
So
stocks and bonds still sound preferable to
me as investments.
But what if someone did take up comic book
collecting? What about storing and
preserving them?
If you're going to keep a comic book for a
collection,
it's important to
handle it carefully,
and
if you're going to keep it, you should bag
it up
at least in a plastic bag.
If you have a comic book that's worth
over 50, 100, you might want to invest in
bags
of a type of plastic in which a lot of the
things that would be in a plastic that
would potentially cause the comic to
deteriorate in fifty or a hundred years
would be neutralized.
If you want to go further along, if you
have comic books that are worth hundreds
of dollars,
there are
things in the paper, the process of making
paper that will eventually cause it to
rot. You can have the the stuff you know
de acidified.
But there's no point in doing this with
just you know every comic book on the
shelf. And actually, if you don't have any
errors and you don't plan to be, you know,
donating these to a library or something,
comic books, if they're handled properly,
are going to outlive you, most likely.
So there's no real danger involved.
They they should be you know kept
kept you know in a away from high humidity
and excessive, you know, extremes of
temperature, and kept in a dry and cool
place and kept out of direct sunlight.
Wayne pointed out to us that there's been
a big change in the comic book industry in
the past few years, one that will affect
collectors.
The biggest thing that's happened comic
books recently is probably the biggest
thing that's happened since comic books
began,
is that the ownership of some of the
characters is now being held by the
individual creators in much the same way
that that
a
publisher does not own a novel by Isaac
Asimov, Isaac Asimov would own the
copyright.
And now comic books are coming out where
the writer or the artist or both
own the copyright to the character, and
the publisher is publishing it for them in
the same kind of a relationship that a
book publisher has with a novelist.
And this is a complete change in the
former system of the publisher owning
everything, everything being done on the
work for higher basis, as though the
artist was just coming in and doing the
same type of function as sweeping the
floors inside the corporate offices.
This is uh
going to be a change that's going to
become more and more evident
in the next few years, and is going to
create a lot of more excitement within the
comic book field.
We'll talk more about comics with Bob
Wayne on our next show.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.
Coming up next is the Science Fiction
Radio Show, so stay with us.
And here are your hosts.
Comic book collecting has become a rage
recently. The prices of some collectible
comics have risen almost 1,000% in just a
few years. On
our last show, Bob Wayne explained some
things about comic book collecting and
advised the unwary newcomer to be
extremely cautious when entering the
field.
This means a comic book artist could
change publishing companies and move to
where he can get the best contract.
We asked Wayne what this change would mean
to collectors, and he gave us an
interesting answer.
I have to go back a little bit.
The other thing that has changed the comic
book industry is the change in
distribution.
Where at one time all the comic books
pretty much were available at 7-Elevens
and drug stores. And
a 7-Eleven bought them from a distributor,
the same people have used it that handled
TV guide and Time magazine and such
things.
And this meant that the publishers had to
print, just like on anything else, had
to print, you know, let's say 500,000 and
they sold 200,000, and 300,000 got thrown
away.
With the rise of specialty shops that sell
comic books and science fiction books,
those shops order their comics in a
different fashion.
They order them non returnable.
They get a better discount, but they have
to keep everything they order.
And it's now to the point where a lot of
comic book titles are being published only
in the non-returnable format.
So if a person's only buying their comic
books at a 7-Eleven or in a small town
that doesn't have a specialty store, there
are a number of titles they would never
have seen. In fact, there are titles that
are being published only for specially
store distribution
that are selling better than some of the
comic books that have distribution in both
forms.
Examples of this would be Camelot 3000
from DC Comics,
which takes the King Arthur saga and
brings it back to life, but in the year
3000.
And the thing with the book like Star
Slayer, which is written and drawn by Mike
Grell, who used to work for DC Comics
doing The Warlord, is that Mike Grill owns
the copyright, the Star Slayer.
And it's, you know, the fact that Mike
Grill owns the copyright means that when
his contract with the publisher Pacific
Comics expired with issue number six, he
was able to find a better deal and make
more money for himself and take it to
First Comics, a new publishing company out
of Chicago,
for starting with issue number seven.
Wayne says this change, which allows a
comic book character to switch publishing
companies, is a very recent one, and he
likens it to the situation that exists in
book publishing.
The idea that a person could move a
character from one company to another for
a better financial deal
had never occurred in anyone a few years
ago under the old system of publishing.
But in the same way in book publishing,
then not every novel by an author
necessarily is going to come out from the
same publisher.
There's no reason for every issue of a
comic book to come out from the same
publisher.
Some of the ramifications of this new
situation should be obvious to collectors.
One difference may well be that a
collector devoted to a particular
character or artist will have to follow
him through a number of publishing
companies. Perhaps a collector will be
required to buy more issues too, in order
to acquire a complete set of something.
Also, it should be more difficult to
locate and catalog characters and artists,
since they will probably be spread out
over more companies.
But for dedicated comic book collectors,
the new situation may be a beneficial one
after all.
Sure. With more competition, there will
likely be more comics and more artists,
and therefore more material for collectors
to work with.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Permian Mason
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas.
Coming up next is the Science Fiction
Radio Show, so stay with us.
And here are your hosts.
Poetry and science fiction, two unlikely
candidates for a merger, but they go
together very well.
As practitioners of the art and members of
the science fiction poetry association
will tell you.
I think about 1974 was when the term was
first used, and it was coined by uh uh
well, it wasn't coined by anybody, but it
was just used as a label by Peter
Dillingham, who was of uh uh an early uh
uh prosodist and theorist of science
fiction poetry and uh Stephen Greggs, who
edited uh Eternity Science
Fiction, which was the first science
fiction
magazine to really incorporate
poetry as an integral part of uh its
format. What is science fiction poetry?
Well,
uh, I really can't say what science
fiction poetry is in terms of a definition
because no one has ever defined science
fiction or poetry, so science fiction
poetry has no real definition.
But I generally tend to class science
fiction poetry as something containing
uh an element which is usually associated
with
science fiction,
you know, in other words, uh
speculative element of uh outer space or
of uh biology or of time or whatnot.
So that's
that's my loose definition.
It's important to realize that what we
now are calling science fiction poetry has
been written in in uh the so-called
mainstream for a long time.
William Blake
is a uh really primary example of someone
who wrote mystical poetry, but in order to
do it, he created alternate worlds and an
ability to travel between this world or
the world of London that he knew and his
imaginary uh England, which he called
Albion. Okay.
Well, that's that's fantasy.
That's science fiction, that's alternate
world uh uh imagination.
Okay. Uh in more modern times, there's W.
H. Auden, who has written a number of
poems which uh would be uh uh
scientifically oriented as well as science
fictional because they speculate about
eventual results of of uh
scientific
discoveries. Uh,
one of the most
striking examples of
what I would call
science
fiction
poetry is uh
something that was done by
Richard
Wilbur,
a well-established uh
mainstream poet, and
this
poem is called The Mind Reader.
This is a poem about
a person who actually reads
minds and
he makes his living
by
reading minds.
Now, I don't think Richard Wilbur would
call it science fiction, although
maybe in the back of his mind,
he's working with uh
the idea that, well, this is usually a
science fiction theme,
but it's really a very well-done poem.
And the point about
science fiction poetry and mainstream
poetry is that
that to be a good poem, a science fiction
poem must first be a good poem. Okay,
and then content-wise,
it diverges from what we normally
recognize or would normally class as
mainstream poetry.
The science fiction poetry association was
founded in 1978 by Suzette Hayden Elgin, a
mainstream novelist, who saw there was no
meeting point for poets in the science
fiction field.
There are a number of well-known science
fiction writers who were members of the
Science Fiction Poetry Association.
Theodore Sturgeon, Ursula LeGwin, Gregory
Benford, Ed Bryant, and Gene Wolfe are a
few.
It seems to work
out that way, but
percentage-wise, it's
probably
well, seventy-five percent I would say,
but I should think it should be ninety
in one sense,
and I feel it's uh it shows that we do
have at least twenty-five percent
membership of people who just um are
interested in poetry altogether.
Which is healthy.
I mean, we're we're
not trying to be separate
from the
the mainstream of literary uh literary
mainstream with poetry, that's for sure.
What's the difference between regular
poetry and science fiction poetry?
Well, there's several arguments about
that. I think my basic uh
my basic viewpoint is is that if
it's
science fiction or fantasy poetry if it's
published within that genre.
And uh,
because a lot of the poetry
really doesn't necessarily have to have
unicorns or spaceships in it.
A lot of it can be um
about
very peripheral things.
I'd call them speculative things.
We asked Frazier for an example of
something speculative.
Well, have you ever picked up a telephone
and heard someone talking on the line
somewhere far in the distance?
It's another conversation between two
other people.
Well, say you wrote a poem about
about that in the context of like there
were telephone ghosts.
They
kind of live in the telephone line, okay.
That
would be a mainstream poem, or it could be
a science fiction poem because it it deals
sort of in that
the uh
the same
realm that uh
imagination
that
fantastic
imagination is in.
We asked Gene Van Troyer, science fiction
poet and author, if there was anything in
style or technique that distinguished
regular poetry from science fiction
poetry.
Any style can be used.
You can you can use it in in very rigidly
metered and rhymed
uh
poetic forms, uh, which we usually call
traditional poetic forms,
sestinas,
uh sonnets,
villainiles,
and so forth,
or you can use the uh uh
free verse,
or the
modern uh uh
poetic techniques that uh uh
you would see, say
William Carlos Williams using or Charles
Olsen using.
We asked Bob Frazier to give us some
titles of books and magazines that contain
science fiction poetry.
Well, I suggest a book called Holding Your
Eight Hands.
It's been reprinted
as a paperback by Doubleday last year.
Originally was published in 1969.
The editor is Edward Lucy Smith, and it's
a collection of science fiction poetry.
Um
an international collection, actually,
although not widely international as
British and I think some Australian
authors and American authors in it.
Um
there's an anthology of poetry coming out
from uh
a man here in Denver,
Steve Rasnick Tim,
and it's an offshoot of uh
a magazine he's been editing of
speculative poetry for three or four
years. It's called the Umbril Anthology,
and uh
it will use
poetry out of what I see as the history of
science fiction poetry.
There's also coming up an anthology in a
couple of years by uh
Bruce McAllister and Dick Allen, who are
both writers of science fiction poetry and
both people who uh work in academic jobs
in the United States,
uh who which are is going to attempt to do
the same thing, create a comprehensive
anthology of some sort.
And
there is Starline,
which is our newsletter, which publishes
original poetry, markets.
We have a workshop in there, we
have news uh related to science fiction
and poetry, uh we have letter columns and
everything that basically ties our
organization
together. We'll conclude our discussion of
science fiction and poetry on our next
show.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas,
coming up next is the science fiction
radio show, so stay with us.
This is the Science Fiction Radio Show, a
commentary on science fiction and fantasy.
And here are your hosts.
This is Darrell Lane
and David Carson.
This will be our final show on science
fiction and poetry and on the Science
Fiction Poetry Association.
The Science Fiction Poetry Association was
founded as a formal organization in 1978.
Its members, which include some big name
science fiction authors, believe that
science fiction and poetry are a natural
blend.
Does science fiction
poetry have anything to offer that regular
poetry doesn't? We
asked this question of Bob Frasier, editor
of the Science Fiction Poetry Association
newsletter, Starline.
Yes,
today
science has found some things about the
universe, especially let's use physics as
an example.
Or found some things because science has
become so specialized,
and that any scientist today is almost a
specialist in this field.
But let's pick physics, okay.
And these are things which cannot be
systematically and rationally explained.
And you will find in the scientific texts
that are discussing these possibilities.
These are kind of rips in Einsteinian
spacetime continuum or however you want to
look at them, they're anomalies.
And because poem poetry can in a small
space
deal with something which can be abstract.
It doesn't always have to be abstract and
doesn't have to be unreadable and it
doesn't have to be boring, but because it
can deal with some things that are
abstract in a small amount of space.
Poetry can be
or poetic talk, even if it's in a prose
sense,
or even in a speech,
can deal with with abstract things nicely.
I think represents
of a refusion of
science
and
poetry.
And this is a totally artificial
separation
because uh
poetic expression
comes from the same wellsprings that the
ordering process we see in science comes
from.
It's the need to put
order on the universe. Well,
in the Renaissance,
you didn't see
this uh this really
drastic split between science and art.
They were viewed as being the same thing.
But I mentioned William Blake earlier, and
it seems to me that around the time of
William Blake, disillusionment with the
industrial revolution in science was
already setting in, and William Blake is
rabidly anti-science.
And uh personally I feel that that he was
mistaken in this particular aspect, but he
looked in the world, he looked around the
world that he saw, and and things were
terrible. Uh, people were uh enslaved
almost by the industrial system, and
and he was just rabidly opposed to it
because it oppressed the spirit
and oppressed the soul.
Well,
now
I think this is a forerunner of the split
that that gradually grew from about the
19th century uh
the latter part of the 18th century up and
th up until the present time in the 20th
century,
but it's gradually coming back together,
and you see a lot more
science showing up in poetry and poets
feeling much more confident about
expressing you
know things out of science in their
poetry, as well as scientists
falling back on poetry to explicate
things.
This has been the science fiction radio
show, a production of the Permian Basin
Science Fiction Association, produced in
conjunction with Odessa College in Odessa,
Texas,
and the city of the city of the What